This is wrong. I mean, it's a spiralized
hot dog, so it's wrong for lots of reasons.
But according to Binging with Babish, this is
the maximum possible surface area you can get
when cooking a hot dog. And that is definitely
wrong, and I can prove it mathematically. Hey,
what's up guys and welcome back to Babish's
Great American Hot Dog Adventure. So,
without further ado, let's start doing things
to sausage. First up, the spiralizer. Basically,
we're impaling your sausage on a wooden skewer
and then placing a single cut diagonally down
the length of your sausage, making sure to
cut all the way down to the skewer. Then,
once your sausage has been spiralized, we're going
to gently separate the layers, pulling it down the
length [music] of the skewer until evenly spaced.
Then, just to improve browning, we're going to hit
it with a little bit of non-stick spray before
heading out [music] to our preheated grill,
where we're going to grill it up just like any
other hot dog with one vital difference. I did the
math and this has about 15,000% more surface area.
15,000 15,000 15,000 [__] 15,000% increase. Now,
I know a lot of you are going to say Babish is
just joking around and it's comedic exaggeration,
but no, I'm going to take it seriously. If this
is our standard issue hot dog, which I'm going to
approximate as a cylinder, we're going to ignore
ignore the caps for now. And this is a spiralized
hot dog where you still have all the same original
surface area, but now you have the new exposed cut
surface area. We can calculate the area of that
internal cut. The reason we can do that is because
this cut is a well-known mathematical
shape. This, my friends, is a helicoid.
If you swing a radial line all the way around
360°, you get a nice flat disc. But we don't want
that. We want a spiral. So, what we can do instead
is add just a little bit of upwards movement as
the radius goes around. So, now it's gradually
spiraling up the axis. So, now, as well as the
size of the radius, we can also mess around with
how much it goes up and down the axis for each
sweep. So, well, let's have a nice tight one like
that. And then we continue to spin it around. And
this mathematical surface is called the helicoid.
Here we have our idealized theoretical hot dog
represented by this cylinder. And if we want to do
that spiral cut, sure enough, it's a helyco. Look
at it go all the way along. And because of the way
it hugs and kind of wraps around that central axis
here, that's exactly how Babish did the cut. The
knife rotates around the central skewer and forms
this exact helicoid shape. All we need now is a
formula to calculate its area. Back like when we
just had the standard issue flat circle, you
can calculate the area of the circle a couple
ways. You could use the parametric equations
for that entire surface. Or you could just use
the function and you integrate across all 360°
around and the radius all the way out. and you
get your classic formula for the area of a disc.
Okay, so now what we're going to do is just add
in that extra dimension. So parametrically we've
just got a third coordinate that scales up with
whatever our ratio is for the distance up that
it goes for every revolution around the axis. And
ultimately we'll have to factor in how many times
we go around. That's just part of the integration.
You could use the parametric equations. You could
do this integral. And if you do the integration,
which you can do on your own time, you get
this. I know it's not pretty. Integration very
rarely is. I mean, there's a shine, an inverse
shine in there. Look, I'm as angry as anyone,
but the point is, if you put in the radius of
your heliocoid, you put in the amount it goes
up per revolution, the number of revolutions, you
can exactly calculate its area. The one thing to
bear in mind now is once we've done the helicoid
cut down the hot dog, we actually stretch it out.
And I'm just using this kind of hashing to show
the open bits in the spiralized hot dog. And so
now we've actually doubled the surface area.
Now, as we enjoy the helicoid swooping by,
you need to bear in mind because we've stretched
it out. The original cut, there it goes, has been
split into two surfaces. So, we've just got to
double the number that comes out of the standard
area formula. We can now put some numbers in using
what I'm going to call the standard hot dog. Now,
we had a close look at Babish's video. We think
they're using a 6-in long hot dog, which is about
an inch in diameter. Actually, doesn't really
matter. As long as we're consistent, everything
kind of cancels out. But, we are going to switch
to metric. So, we're going to call that 152.4 mm
long. And we're going to call it a radius of 12.7
mm out from the exact center of that cylinder. And
if you calculate the area, no cap, then that is
a total of 121.6 cm squared area. That's what we
start with. Now, when we go up to the spiralized
one, we still have that same outer area that
hasn't changed, but we get all this new internal
area. That's the increase. And we can we can
calculate that. We put the same numbers into that
terrible helicoid formula from before. And you get
an area of 140.6 cm squared, which is bigger.
So, you do get a bigger increase in area than
the original area. It's more than doubled. Has it
gone up by 15,000%. No, it's gone up by 115.6%.
So, I know we were all shocked. Uh, so
it turns out off off by at least an order
of magnitude. In a moment, I'm going to show
you my alternative to the spiralized hot dog,
and it is as horrifying as it is genius. No,
no, no, no. Before that, I want to thank the
sponsor of this video, Private Internet Access,
a VPN, which much like you don't have to trust
Babish's claims about a spiralized hot dog. You
can check them for yourself. You don't have to
trust their claims that they don't keep any logs
of the traffic you put through their VPN. Now,
some people are happy with the fact that in
court when they've been asked to hand over logs,
they haven't because they don't keep them.
But if you really want to check for yourself,
all of their code is on GitHub. It's open. You
can go look at it. I mean, you probably won't,
but other nerds have. And we know without any
doubt. If you want maximum privacy, private
internet access discount [music] code standup
maths does not keep any logs. Although, actually,
yeah, that code, I wonder if there's a way you
could save some money on it. Yes, this whole time,
Chef Matt has actually been I business Matt here
to say, use the QR code on the screen now or the
discount code standup mass for 86% off and you
can get up to 4 months free. That works out to
like a 57 a month. I mean, I think I'm paying
more than that. I should use my own discount
code. Huge thanks to Private Internet Access
for sponsoring this video. Now, before we get
to my suggestions for what's superior to a spiral,
could you actually achieve 15,000% extra surface
area with this method? Well, technically, yes.
You just have to get thinner and thinner slices,
as in like the increase per rotation gets smaller
and smaller. Fun fact, it means in the limit,
you can approximate the area of a helioid as
just a series of discs. You're just basically
adding up a whole bunch of circles. And were you
to have 1,800 circles, that's how many rotations
the knife would have to do. Yeah, you would have
15,000% more surface area. But those cuts would
be separated by 0.085 mm of sausage skin, which uh
you basically have just a minced sausage. the the
cylinder uh at that point would not be would
not be unharmed. You know what's easier than
a helioid both cutting it and calculating its
area? A rectangle. What if we just cut the hot
dog lengthwise? I [music] mean leaving at least
one end intact because I think whatever we do,
we need a contiguous like single piece hot dog.
Otherwise, you may as well just dice it up. But if
you were to cut in the middle and then all the way
down like a rectangle, easy to compute the area
and easy to cut. So let's see how that works. So
I'm going to start by making a rectangular cut the
entire length of the hot dog, which if we work out
the area of this and double it for both sides for
our standard hot dog, that's an extra 77.4 square
cm exposed. So already inside there is an extra
63.7% surface area. But why stop? We're going to
rotate it a third of the way around. And I'm going
to do another one all the way down here. That's
adding another 77.4 square cm of area for now. A
total of 127.3% extra area. And one more. Now two
already more than the Babish spiral. But if we've
got space over here for a third one down here,
that's now 191% more area. And you're thinking,
well, Matt, hang on. The area is on the inside. We
got to cook that. Well, now I'm going to complete
all the cuts to the end just on one end. So, we
still have this one here to keep it a contiguous
dog. But if I split all of those out, I give
you the six-legged squid sausage. Now, I wanted
to call this the hot pod after an oc octopus pod
for feet, but apparently uh this is a sepha dog.
There you are, the six-legged sephila dog for an
extra 191% surface area. I can keep jiggling it if
that helps. Um, I'm getting a lot of negative
energy from everyone else here. Nom. Oh no.
The Babish spiral 116% extra surface area.
Rounding up the sephila dog. 191% extra
surface area. Not only is there more area, it's
more adorable. Look at it. Eat me. It's not as
terrifying as people have claimed it is. And
these horizontal cuts, would you believe it,
are always better. So, so far we've taken the
coil to just be roughly what Babish did in the
video. And then for this, I've just done as many
lengthwise cuts as we needed to get significantly
more surface area. But what if we take like
the gap between the cuts as a fixed value? So,
you're prepared to cut a certain width here and
you end up cutting a certain width here. How would
it look if you compared all possible spirals to
all possible sephila dogs? I calculated the ratio
of the spiralized increase in area versus the
sephila dog increase in area for a whole range of
different cut separation values. And I'm going to
put them on this plot. And because it's a ratio,
if the line is above one, that means that spiral
is better. If it's below one, it means sephloid
dog is better. And the line looks like this.
Now, as you can see, it's completely under one,
which means that a sephloid dog cut for a given
spacing of cuts is always better than a spiralized
cut. Now, it starts off twice as good, but that's
for impossibly small cuts. And as the cut spacing
gets bigger and bigger, the ratio gets closer
and closer to one, but it never crosses one.
The sephila dog is always better. And the reason
it looks like an up and down like saw function is
because when you're cutting through the the the
sephila dog, you can you got to round it because
you work out the spacing and you do the maximum
number you can fit at that spacing or greater. So
you get the step function whenever you can just
fit in one more cut. However, if you were to
approximate both of these, you can see the value
of two drops out incredibly nicely. The general
equation for lots of rectangular cuts is just
the area of a rectangle, the length of it, and
twice the radius, that's the diameter. And then we
have to multiply that by how many cuts there are,
which is the circumference divided by the
separation. And we round that down to the nearest
whole number of cuts, which is not a very nice
formula, but compare it to the helioite. Uh, what
a mess. Although both of these can be simplified.
So we could say for the heliocoid area we know in
the limit you could just multiply discs. So swap
it out for the area of a circle, multiply it by
how many there are, which is the length divided
by the spacing. Pretty straightforward. You know
what? We can probably simplify the sephlog one
as well. Instead of rounding down in the limit,
we'll just allow fractional cuts. Even though it
doesn't physically work, it's an approximation.
Wait a minute. we rearrange these, they're the
same. If you approximate both of these wildly
different looking equations for area once they're
both simplified down, it's the identical equation,
but with that two and that proves in the limit,
the sephila dog is precisely twice as good as the
Babish spiral. Maths. Ah, delicious. Now, the
Sepha dog has a lot of features. more surface
area. Looks adorable. And check this out. Makes
dogs appear. However, All right. All right. All
right. On your bed. Yes, there is one downside to
the Sepha dog. And it's though, even though the
legs are delicious and crispy, it's not the same
all the way along. By the time you get to this
end, that's just a big chunk of regular hot dog.
What a disappointment. If only there was a way you
could cut up a hot dog to have all the advantage
of the sephila dog with none of the disadvantage
of the chunk. And there is. I've cracked it. This
may be my greatest invention ever. I have come up
with the fractal fertter. It's a fractal hot
dog which solves the discontinuous crispiness
problem. Moreover, the fractal furter has even
more area because we're going to do four cuts.
Now, to do that, we're going to use the fact
that because of how hot dogs are packaged,
they're basically cross-sectional squares.
They're cuboids. Ignore that. That invalidates
all our cylinder assumptions up until now. And
I'm going to do them in two pairs of cuts. So,
the very first cut, I'm going to use the
seams, if you will, on the hot dog. If I
go all the way through there and come out on the
opposite seam, and then do the lengthwise cut,
that should be right the whole way down. I can
now, there we go, do its partner cut at 90 degrees
to that one. So I come in through this seam out
the opposite one. Yes. Cut all the way along. And
what I end up with, you could call a four-legged
sephila dog. There it is. But what I'm going to
do is to complete it, I'm going to rotate it.
So instead of going out this end, I'm going to
come out this end. And I'm going to do the other
pair of cuts exactly in between the ones I just
did. So if I start here on the middle of the flat
surface and go all the way down very carefully,
I don't want to accidentally cut off a leg and
out the far end there. And then rotate and do the
other one at 90° to that one. So I go in here all
the way down. Now, the trick is to make sure you
cut out the opposite side at the same time. There
we are. Let me just triple check this cut. That
one's good as well. So, now I have a continuous
ring of hot dog meat known as the fractal furter.
Look at that. That That's art. I don't care what
anyone says. Look at that. Come on. There it is.
The fully cooked fractal furter. Also attracts
dogs. And as you can see, if I'm very careful
here, this is still one like continuous piece of
hot dog, but equally crispy in all directions.
And because we have four lengthwise cuts, that's
a total of over 300 square cm of extra area. This
is a 254.6% 6% increase on area. This blows the
spiral out of the water. If you wanted to go all
the way up to an extra 15,000%, well, then you're
going to need 236 cuts. 118 to one end and 118 to
the other end. That'd be spaced by 0.17 mm each,
which is bordering on plausible. I don't think
it's going to work. Anyway, I think this is as
good as it gets. And honestly, I made this. I was
just marking around. I thought this was going to
be some ridiculous, you know, troll hot dog, but
this is genuinely fun to make, actually enjoyable
to cook and delicious. So, if anyone, please do
try this. Send me photos of you having a fractal
furter. And if anyone can come up with a better
way to expose area in a hot dog, I would like
to hear it. But until then, this reigns supreme.
That is delicious on every scale. Oh, and thanks
to Private Internet Access for sponsoring
this incredibly serious educational video.